罗马帝国在全盛时期的版图
由非洲沙漠延伸至
英格兰北部边境
罗马皇帝更掌控了全世界
三分之一以上人口的生杀大权
在西元180年的冬天，奥里勒斯皇帝
12年征战、讨伐日耳曼野蛮部落的行动
即将宣告结束
只要扫平最后一处据点
罗马大军便可获得胜利
而帝国从此将永享太平
“日耳曼”
长官
Sir.
将军
General.
- General.
- Sir.
长官
又累又饿
Lean and hungry.
- 还是没动静？
- 完全没有
- Still nothing?
- Not a sign.
- 他去多久了？
- 快两个小时
- How long has he been gone?
- Nearly two hours.
长官，他们会接受吗？
Will they fight, sir?
我们很快就会知道了
We shall know soon enough.
士兵，把投石器往前推
Soldier, I said to move
those catapults forward.
- 它们离射程太远了
- 射程没问题
- They're out of range.
- The range is good.
- 会误伤骑兵队
- 你不用担心，明白吗？
- The danger to the cavalry.
- Is acceptable. Agreed?
对方不接受
They say no.
Steady. Steady.
做人要认命
People should know when they're conquered.
昆塔斯，你会吗？
Would you, Quintus?
我会吗？
Would I?
勇气和荣誉
- Strength and honor.
收到信号就发动攻击
At my signal, unleash hell.
投石器准备
Load the catapults.
步兵团成进攻队形
Infantry form up for advance.
- 弓箭手预备
- 弓箭手
- Archers ready.
- Archers.
搭箭！
- Knock.
兄弟们！
Patres.
麦希穆斯！
Maximus.
三个星期以后，我会在田里收割农作物
Three weeks from now, I will
be harvesting my crops.
想像你要去的地方，愿望就快要实现了
Imagine where you will be, and it will be so.
不要退却，跟着我冲
Hold the line. Stay with me.
如果发现自己落单了
If you find yourself alone,
迎着阳光，独自驰骋在草原上时…
riding in green fields
with the sun on your face,
不用担心
do not be troubled.
那是因为你在天堂，而且你已经阵亡了
For you are in Elysium,
and you're already dead.
兄弟们…
Brothers,
我们生平的事迹…
what we do in life
将永垂不朽
echoes in eternity.
- Pull.
用力拉！
Pull.
长官，投石器准备就绪！
Catapults ready, sir.
弓箭手，点火！
Archers, ignite.
点火！
- Ignite.
弓箭手，拉弓！
Archers, draw.
放箭！
Loose.
弟兄们，准备！
All right, men, ready.
不要退却！
Hold the line.
放箭！
Loose. Loose.
填装弹药！
Reload.
不要退却！
Hold the line.
- 拉弓！
- 放箭！
- Draw.
- Loose.
跟着我冲！
Stay with me.
罗马万岁！
Roma Victor.
普利托里亚十四世
你认为他是不是快死了？
Do you think he's really dying?
十年来，他一直都是这个样子
He's been dying for ten years.
不然他为什么要召见我们
If he weren't really dying,
he wouldn't have sent for us.
也许是因为想念我们
Maybe he just misses us.
那元老会的议员呢？
没事不会传唤他们的，除非…
The senators? He wouldn't
have summoned them if...
康莫德斯，别吵
Peace, Commodus.
上路两个星期以来
你老是疑神疑鬼的，烦死我了
After two weeks on the road, your
incessant scheming is hurting my head.
他已经做好决定而且就要宣布了
He's made his decision.
He's going to announce it.
他会任命我
He will name me.
我要做的第一件事就是…
The first thing I shall do when...
举办大型的竞技比赛来荣耀他
is honor him with games
worthy of His Majesty.
目前，我最想做的就是洗个热水澡
For now, the first thing I
shall do is have a hot bath.
陛下
Your Highness?
看样子我们就快到了
We seem to be almost there, sir.
- 殿下
- 皇帝他人在哪？
- Sire.
- Where's the Emperor?
他在前线，陛下，军队已经开拔19天了
He's at the front, sire.
They've been gone for 19 days.
还是不断的有伤兵回来
The wounded are still coming in.
牵马来
My horse.
殿下
My lord.
祝我好运
A kiss?
麦希穆斯，你又再次证明了你的勇气
You have proved your
valor yet again, Maximus.
希望这是最后一次
Let us hope for the last time.
陛下，敌人全军覆没
There's no one left to fight, sire.
永远不可以掉以轻心
There is always someone left to fight.
我该如何奖励，罗马最伟大的将军
How can I reward Rome's greatest general?
准许我回家
Let me go home.
哦！回家
Home.
陛下，他们在向您致敬
They honor you, Caesar.
是向你致敬，麦希穆斯，他们尊敬你
It's for you, Maximus. They honor you.
我错过了吗？我是否错过了
Have I missed it? Have I missed the battle?
你错过了这场战役
You have missed the war.
父亲，恭喜您
Father, congratulations.
我应该奉献一百头公牛
来表达对您凯旋的敬意
I shall sacrifice a hundred
bulls to honor your triumph.
那倒是不必
Save the bulls.
向麦希穆斯致敬吧，是他打赢这场仗的
Honor Maximus. He won the battle.
- 将军
- 殿下
- General.
- Highness.
罗马向你致敬，我则以兄弟的身份拥抱你
Rome salutes you, and I
embrace you as a brother.
老朋友，好久不见
It has been too long, my old friend.
殿下
Highness.
父亲，让我来扶您
Here, Father. Take my arm.
我想我应该离开了
I think it is time for me to leave.
这就是罗马的未来
So much for the glory of Rome.
了不起的一仗
Magnificent battle.
Three of our legions against
four thousand of them.
将军，还活着？
Still alive?
- 还活着
- 天上的神是有幽默感的
- Still alive.
- The gods must have a sense of humor.
- 他们一定特别眷顾你
- 维勒瑞斯
- The gods must love you.
- Valerius.
将军，您要回兵营还是回罗马？
Back to barracks, General? Or to Rome?
回家，我的妻儿和田地在等我
Home. My wife, the son, the harvest.
我还是无法想像麦希穆斯当农夫的样子
Maximus the farmer. I still
have difficulty imagining that.
昆塔斯，身上沾到尘土要比血迹容易洗掉
You know, dirt cleans off a
lot easier than blood, Quintus.
- 他在这里
- 殿下
- Here he is.
- Highness.
议员盖尔斯、议员佛可
Senator Gaius, Senator Falco.
你要小心盖尔斯，他会替你洗脑
Beware of Gaius. He'll pour
a honeyed potion in your ear,
然后有一天，你会突然高呼“共和国万岁”
and you'll wake up one day, and all
you'll say is, "Republic, republic."
有何不可？毕竟罗马创建时是共和国
Well, why not? Rome was
founded as a republic.
没错，况且共和国是由元老院来执政
Yes, and in a republic,
the Senate has the power.
当然啦！盖尔斯议员绝不是因此才从政的
Senator Gaius isn't influenced
by that, of course.
将军，你支持谁呢？皇帝还是元老院？
Where do you stand,
General? Emperor or senate?
议员，军人的职责是保卫国家、上阵杀敌
The soldier has the advantage of being able
to look his enemy in the eye, Senator.
有身后的军队支持，你要从政易如反掌
Well, with an army behind you,
you could be extremely political.
让我来帮你解围，二位，失陪一下
I warned you. Now I shall save you. Senators.
麦希穆斯
Maximus.
我将会需要你的帮助
I'm going to need good men like you.
殿下，我又能帮你什么？
How may I be of service, Highness?
只有你才知道该如何指挥军队
You're a man who knows what it is to command.
在你的领导下，无人不服、战无不克
You give your orders, the orders
are obeyed and the battle is won.
但那些议员只会算计、争辩、奉承还有欺骗
But these senators scheme and
squabble and flatter and deceive.
麦希穆斯，我的朋友
我们得从政客手中解救罗马
We must save Rome from the
politicians, my friend.
一旦等到时机来临，你会帮我吗？
Can I count on you, when the time comes?
殿下，只要你父亲准我退役，我打算立刻回家
Highness, when your father releases
me, I intend to return home.
回家？你是应该回家看看
Home? Well, no one's earned it more.
可别耽于安逸，我很快就会需要你
Don't get too comfortable. I
may call on you before long.
你知道吗？露西拉也来了
Lucilla's here. Did you know?
她对你还是念念不忘
She's not forgotten you.
你现在是英雄了
And now you're the great man.
要是你是男人就好了
If only you had been born a man.
你会是个了不起的皇帝
What a Caesar you would have made.
父亲
Father.
你够坚强
You would have been strong.
可是我在想，你够公正吗？
I wonder, would you have been just?
我不会辜负你对我的期望
I would have been what you taught me to be.
旅途还愉快吧？
How was your journey?
又长又不舒服，为什么要我来？
Long. Uncomfortable. Why have I come?
跟你弟弟有关，我需要你帮忙
I need your help. With your brother.
当然
Of course.
他爱你，他一向如此
He loves you. He always has.
另外…
And...
现在会是他最需要你的时候
he will need you now, more than ever.
别谈政治了
Enough of politics.
我们何不假装你是个乖女儿…
Let us pretend that you are a loving daughter
而我则是个好父亲
and I am a good father.
多么愉快的假象，不是吗？
This is a pleasant fiction, isn't it?
早安
Good morning, General.
再给我三匹马
I need three warhorses.
二、三！
Two. Three.
四！
Four.
一、二！
One. Two.
皇帝，您要召见我？
You sent for me, Caesar?
- 陛下？
- 麦希穆斯，我要你告诉我
- Caesar?
- Tell me again, Maximus.
为什么我们会在这里？
Why are we here?
陛下，是为了帝国的荣誉
For the glory of the Empire, sire.
哦！没错
Ah, yes.
对，我记起来了
Ah, yes, I remember.
看到那份地图了吗？麦希穆斯
Do you see that map, Maximus?
是我创造了地图上的世界
That is the world which I created.
25年来…
For 25 years,
我南征北讨、半生戎马才有今天的局面
I have conquered, spilt
blood, expanded the Empire.
从我即位以来，印象中只有四年没有战争
Since I became Caesar, I've
known four years without war.
20年中，只有四年是和平的
Four years of peace in 20.
是为了什么？
And for what?
我带来死亡，如此而已
I brought the sword. Nothing more.
陛下，您的功绩…
Caesar, your life...
拜托，别那样叫我
Please. Please don't call me that.
请过来
Come. Please.
过来坐下
Come sit.
让我们好好谈谈…
Let us talk together now,
纯粹是男人间的闲聊
very simply, as men.
麦希穆斯…
Well, Maximus?
说吧！
Talk.
我有五千名士兵待在外面冰冻的泥地上
5,000 of my men are out
there in the freezing mud.
其中三千名浑身是伤
两千名可能无法活着离开
3,000 are bloodied and cleaved.
2,000 will never leave this place.
我绝不相信他们的牺牲是毫无意义的
I will not believe that they
fought and died for nothing.
那你相信什么呢？
And what would you believe...
他们是为了您和罗马而战
They fought for you. And for Rome.
罗马是什么？
And what is Rome, Maximus?
我看过世界上其他的地方
I've seen much of the rest of the world.
既冷酷又阴暗，罗马代表了光亮
It is brutal and cruel and
dark. Rome is the light.
你从来没去过那里
Yet you have never been there.
你不晓得它现在的样子
You have not seen what it has become.
麦希穆斯，我快死了
I am dying, Maximus.
当你走到人生的尽头…
When a man sees his end,
你会想知道自己这一生的目的
he wants to know there was
some purpose to his life.
死后人们又将如何评价我？
How will the world speak
my name in years to come?
推崇我是位哲学家？
Will I be known as the philosopher?
是名勇士？
The warrior?
还是位暴君？
The tyrant?
或是名让罗马回归自我的皇帝？
Or will I be the emperor who
gave Rome back her true self?
罗马的共和曾经是个梦想
There was once a dream that was Rome.
你只能悄悄的说
You could only whisper it.
再大声一点，它就会消失…
Anything more than a
whisper and it would vanish.
它是如此的不堪一击
It was so fragile.
我担心在残酷的现实环境中
它根本无法存活下去
And I fear that it will
not survive the winter.
麦希穆斯…
Maximus.
现在…
Let us whisper now.
让我们两个说点悄悄话
Together, you and I.
你有个儿子
You have a son.
告诉我你家里的事
Tell me about your home.
我家在提基洛附近的山丘上
My house is in the hills above Tiujillo.
一个非常简单的地方
A very simple place.
在阳光下暖和的红砖屋
Pink stones that warm in the sun.
白天菜园里飘着药草的香味…
A kitchen garden that
smells of herbs in the day,
到了晚上则是茉莉花的味道
jasmine in the evening.
门口有一株高大的白杨树
Through the gate is a giant poplar.
无花果树、苹果树和洋梨树
Figs, apples, pears.
马卡斯，地上的土坯是黑色的
比我太太的头发还黑
The soil, Marcus... black.
Black like my wife's hair.
南坡上种葡萄，北坡是种橄榄
Grapes on the south slopes,
olives on the north.
野生的小马在我家附近玩耍
它们常戏弄我儿子
Wild ponies play near my house. My son,
他想成为它们的一员
he wants to be one of them.
你上次回家是多久的事了？
When was the last time you were home?
两年八个月又二十四天半
Two years, 264 days, and this morning.
麦希穆斯，我羡慕你，你有个幸福的家庭
I envy you, Maximus. It's a good home.
值得你如此牺牲
Worth fighting for.
在你回家之前…
There is one more duty
我希望你履行最后一项义务
that I ask of you before you go home.
皇帝，您希望我做什么？
What would you have me do, Caesar?
我希望你在我死后，成为罗马的保护者
I want you to become the
protector of Rome after I die.
你将得到我全部的授权…
I will empower you to one end alone.
结束危害罗马的贪污腐败…
To give power back to the people of Rome,
将权利还给罗马的人民
and end the corruption that has crippled it.
你愿意接受我授予你的这项荣誉吗？
Well, do you accept this great
honor that I have offered you?
我绝对不能接受
With all my heart, no.
麦希穆斯…
Maximus.
这就是我一定要授权给你的原因
That is why it must be you.
绝对有比我更适合的人选…
But surely a prefect, a senator,
像是元老院的议员
比我了解罗马、懂政治的人
somebody who knows the city,
understands her politics.
可是只有你没被权利腐化
But you have not been
corrupted by her politics.
- 康莫德斯呢？
- 康莫德斯的品德有问题
- And Commodus?
- Commodus is not a moral man.
你应该比谁都清楚
You have known that since you were young.
不能让他统治罗马
Commodus cannot rule.
绝对不可以
He must not rule.
我要是有你这样的儿子就好了
You are the son that I should have had.
康莫德斯会接受我的决定
Commodus will accept my decision.
他知道军队只效忠你
He knows that you command
the loyalty of the army.
陛下，我需要时间考虑
I need some time, sire.
好
Yes.
到日落的时候，我希望你会同意
By sunset, I hope you will have agreed.
现在，以儿子的身份拥抱我
Now embrace me as my son.
顺便帮我多拿一条毛毯
And bring an old man another blanket.
- 我父亲现在只喜欢你
- 夫人
- My father favors you now.
- My lady.
- 以前不是这样的
- 人是会变的
- It was not always so.
- Many things change.
话是没错，但不是每一个人
Many things. Not everything.
麦希穆斯，站住
Maximus, stop.
让我看你的脸
Let me see your face.
- 你看起来很沮丧
- 我损失了许多部下
- You seem upset.
- I lost many men.
我父亲找你有什么事？
What did my father want with you?
是为了在我离开之前跟我道别
To wish me well before I leave for home.
你在说谎
You're lying.
你根本就不会说谎，每次都会被我看出来
I could always tell when you were
lying. You were never any good at it.
- 我一直都不习惯你的安慰
- 没错
- I never acquired your comfort with it.
- True.
反正你也不需要
But then you never had to.
军人的生活是比较简单
Life is more simple for a soldier.
还是你觉得我很无情？
Or do you think me heartless?
我觉得你具备生存的天份
I think you have a talent for survival.
站住，麦希穆斯
Maximus, stop.
见到我真的这么可怕吗？
Is it really so terrible seeing me again?
不是，打完战我觉得很累
No. I'm tired from battle.
看到我父亲如此虚弱，你心里很难过
It hurts you to see my father so fragile.
康莫德斯认为我父亲
会在近日内宣布由他继位
Commodus expects that my father will
announce his succession within days.
你会像追随我父亲一样的对他效忠吗？
Will you serve my brother
as you served his father?
我会永远效忠罗马
I will always serve Rome.
知道吗？
Do you know,
我还是不忘替你祈祷
I still remember you in my prayers.
没错，我有祷告
Oh, yes. I pray.
听到你丈夫去世的消息我很难过，我替他追悼
I was sad to hear of your
husband's death. I mourned him.
- 谢谢你
- 我听说你有个儿子
- Thank you.
- And I hear you have a son.
对，卢赛斯
Yes. Lucius.
他快八岁了
He'll be nearly eight years old.
我儿子也快八岁
My son is also nearly eight.
谢谢你为我祈祷
I thank you for your prayers.
祖先们，我祈求您的指导
Ancestors, I ask for your guidance.
天上的母亲，求您指示我未来的方向
Blessed Mother, come to me with
the gods' desire for my future.
天上的父亲，求您保佑我的妻儿
Blessed Father, watch over my
wife and son with a ready sword.
请转告他们，我因为他们而存在
Whisper to them I live
only to hold them again.
祖先们，我荣耀您
Ancestors, I honor you.
并将恪遵遗训，有尊严的活下去
I will try to live with the
dignity you have taught me.
西斯洛
Cicero.
大人
Sir.
你不觉得履行义务很困难吗？
You don't find it hard to do your duty?
有的时候，我做我想做的事
Sometimes I do what I want to do.
其他的时候，我做我该做的事
The rest of the time, I do what I have to.
我们可能还是不能回家
We may not be able to go home after all.
你预备要履行对罗马的义务了吗？
Are you ready to do your duty for Rome?
是的，父亲
Yes, Father.
你不会成为罗马的皇帝
You will not be Emperor.
是由哪一位更年长、更有智慧的人来取代我
Which wiser, older man is to take my place?
我会将权位传给麦希穆斯
My powers will pass to Maximus,
帝国由他托管
to hold in trust
直到元老院准备好再次治理罗马
until the Senate is ready to rule once more.
罗马会再度成为共和国
Rome is to be a republic again.
- 麦希穆斯
- 对
- Maximus.
- Yes.
我的决定让你很失望？
My decision disappoints you?
您曾写过一封信给我
You wrote to me once,
上面列举了领袖的四项美德
listing the four chief virtues.
智慧…
Wisdom,
公正…
justice,
坚毅…
fortitude,
以及自律
and temperance.
读完信后，我心里明白
我并不具备领袖的特质
As I read the list, I
knew I had none of them.
但是父亲，我有其他的长处
But I have other virtues, Father.
野心
Ambition.
当它驱策我们称霸时，这也能变成一项优点
That can be a virtue when
it drives us to excel.
智谋、勇气
Resourcefulness. Courage.
也许和行军打仗无关
但有其他的方式来表现勇气
Perhaps not on the battlefield, but
there are many forms of courage.
对我的家庭，全心奉献
Devotion. To my family.
还有对你
To you.
可是你完全不欣赏我的优点
But none of my virtues were on your list.
就像你根本不希望有我这样的儿子
Even then it was as if you
didn't want me for your son.
康莫德斯！
Commodus.
你想得太多了
You go too far.
我向天上的诸神祈求
I searched the faces of the gods
让我能够讨您欢心，让您能够以我为荣
for ways to please you, to make you proud.
只要一句赞美…
One kind word,
或是一个拥抱…
one full hug,
把我紧紧的抱在您怀中
where you pressed me to your
chest and held me tight,
都会像慈蔼的阳光，温暖我的心房
would have been like the sun on
my heart for a thousand years.
为什么您如此讨厌我？
What is it in me you hate so much?
康莫德斯
Shh, Commodus.
我不敢有任何奢求…
All I've ever wanted
只求能符合您的期望，陛下
was to live up to you, Caesar.
- 父亲
- 康莫德斯
- Father.
- Commodus.
养子不教…
Your faults as a son
实为父之过啊！
is my failure as a father.
来
Come.
父亲
Father.
为了让您能够爱我…
I would butcher the whole world
即使血洗天下我也在所不惜！
if you would only love me.
麦希穆斯，皇帝有急事找你
Maximus, the Emperor needs you. It's urgent.
兄弟，和我一同哀悼
Lament with me, brother.
我们伟大的父亲去世了
Our great father is dead.
怎么发生的？
How did he die?
医生说是呼吸衰竭
The surgeons say there was no pain.
他在睡梦中安祥的走了
His breath gave out as he slept.
父亲
Father.
麦希穆斯，新皇帝需要你的忠诚
Your emperor asks for your loyalty, Maximus.
效忠于我
Take my hand.
你只有一次机会
I only offer it once.
昆塔斯
Quintus.
我皇万岁
Hail, Caesar.
我必须跟议员们进行会谈
I must talk to the senators.
I need their counsel.
- 去叫醒盖尔斯和佛可
- 盖尔斯跟佛可
- Wake Gaius and Falco.
- Gaius and Falco.
- 我的剑
- 剑
- Sword.
麦希穆斯，请三思而行，你那样做太过轻率
Maximus, please be careful.
That was not prudent.
轻率？皇帝是被人谋杀的
Prudent? The Emperor has been slain.
皇帝是自然死亡的
The Emperor died of natural causes.
- 昆塔斯，你为什么全副武装？
- 警卫
- Why are you armed, Quintus?
- Guards.
麦希穆斯，请你合作
Please don't fight, Maximus.
我很抱歉，是新皇帝下的命令
I'm sorry. Caesar has spoken.
骑马西行…
Ride until dawn
在拂晓之前处决他
and then execute him.
昆塔斯，你看着我，看着我！
Quintus, look at me. Look at me.
答应我，你会好好的照顾我家人
Promise me that you will
look after my family.
他们会在黄泉路上等你
Your family will meet you in the afterlife.
跪下
Kneel.
天上的父亲，求您保佑我的妻儿
Blessed Father, watch over my wife and son.
请转告他们，我因为他们而存在
Whisper to them that I live
only to hold them again.
至少让我死得干净俐落
At least give me a clean death.
死得像个军人
A soldier's death.
有时候，霜会让刀身结冰
The frost. Sometimes it
makes the blade stick.
御卫队
Praetorian.
你上次回家是多久的事了？
When was the last time you were home?
两年八个月又二十四天半
Two years, 264 days, and this morning.
天上的父亲，求您保佑我的妻儿
Blessed Father, watch over my
wife and son with a ready sword.
我会遵照您的意思，试着过着有尊严的生活
I will try to live with the
dignity you have taught me.
转告他们，我因他们而存在
Whisper to them I live
only to hold them again.
世间名利，于我皆如粪土
For all else is dust and air.
转告他们，我因他们而存在
Whisper to them I live
only to hold them again.
世间名利，于我皆如粪土
For all else is dust and air.
爸爸！
别死
Don't die.
你们会再见面的
You'll meet them again.
时候未到
Not yet.
别碰，它们能消毒你的伤口，等着看吧
No. They will clean it. Wait and see.
别死
Don't die.
他们会拿你去喂狮子
They'll feed you to the lions.
它们比我们还值钱
They are worth more than we are.
好一点了吗？
Better now?
看吧！消炎了
Clean. You see?
“祖卡巴，罗马领地”
帕西蒙，我的老朋友
Proximo. My old friend.
每次只要你来这里，那天一定会是个好日子
Every day is a great day when you are here.
不过今天会是你这辈子最幸运的一天
Today is your most fortunate day.
你卖给我的长颈鹿，根本不会交配
- Those giraffes you sold me, they won't mate.
- What?
它们不会交配，只会走来走去、吃个不停
They just walk around eating and not mating.
你卖给我的长颈鹿是同志
You sold me queer giraffes.
- 把钱退还给我
- 做梦
- I want my money back.
- Not a chance.
- 我可以给你特价
- 什么东西特价？
- I do special price for you.
- On what?
你看过我新进的货吗？过来看了再说
Have you seen my new
stock? Come and see them.
他们有谁懂得搏斗，我最近有一场比赛
Do any of them fight? I've
got a match coming up.
有些人能上场搏斗，其他人只能上去送死
Some are good for fighting, others for dying.
我想你两种都需要
You need both, I think.
起来
Get up.
你是做什么的？
What's your trade?
我以前是个猎人
I was a hunter.
我在迦太基附近的盐矿场把他买来的
Oh, no. I bought him from
a salt mine in Carthage.
坐下
Sit down.
军团的标记
Mark of the legion.
罗马元老与人民
- 逃兵
- 有可能，有谁在乎呢？
- Deserter.
- Maybe so. But who cares?
他是西班牙人
He's a Spaniard.
我要六个人，付你一千
I'll take six. for 1,000.
才一千？那个努米迪人就值两千了
1,000? The Numidian alone is worth 2,000.
这群奴隶根本不中用
These slaves are rotten.
人不可貌相
It all adds to the flavor.
等一下！别这样
No. No, no, no. Wait. Wait.
价钱可以再商量
We can negotiate.
我给你两千，另外四千买那些野兽
I'll give you 2,000. And four for the beasts.
既然是老朋友，一共给你五千
That's 5,000 for an old friend.
快一点，还要多久才能回到家？
Come on. How long does it take
to get into my own house?
我是帕西蒙
I am Proximo.
接下来几天，我跟你们会…
I shall be closer to you
for the next few days,
异常的亲近，胜过你们的母亲
which will be last of your miserable lives,
而这几天也将是你们悲惨的
日子结束前，最后的几天
than that bitch of a mother that
brought you screaming into this world.
我不是花钱买你们来作伴的
I did not pay good money
for you for your company.
我付钱是为了从你们的死亡中获利
I paid it so that I could
profit from your death.
你们的人生开始时，有母亲在一旁相伴…
And as your mother was
there at your beginning,
结束时，我会在你们的身旁
so I shall be there at your end.
等到死亡的命运降临时…
And when you die, and die you shall,
你们将因人们的欢呼而升华…
your transition shall be to the sound of...
角斗士…
Gladiators,
我向你们致敬
I salute you.
红色
Red.
黄色
Yellow.
很好
Good.
- 红色
- Red.
西班牙人
Spaniard.
今天到此为止！
That's enough for the moment.
他迟早得认命
His time will come.
下一个
Next.
西班牙人…
Spaniard,
你为什么不还手？
why don't you fight?
我们必须要参加搏斗
We all have to fight.
我不会参加
I don't fight.
我不属于这的，我是个纪录员…
I shouldn't be here. I'm a
scribe, I write down words.
并会说7种语言
I can speak seven languages.
很好
Good.
明天你可以用7种语言尖叫
Tomorrow, you can scream in seven languages.
说不定这个纪录员会获得自由呢
Perhaps the scribe will be
the one who wins his freedom.
自由？
Freedom?
我该怎么做？
What do I have to do?
你上竞技场，然后杀了我
You go in the arena and you kill me.
再杀他…
And him.
还有努米迪人…
And the Numidian,
逃兵
and the deserter.
及上百人
And a hundred more.
只要没有人跟你打，你就自由了
And when there's no more
to fight, you're free.
我做不到
I can't do that.
不行？
我可以
But I can.
那个标记代表你信奉的神？
Is that the sign of your gods?
这样做他们不会生气吗？
Will that not anger them?
你受到天神的眷顾
The gods favor you.
红色代表神的颜色
Red is the gods' color.
今天你会需要他们的帮助
You will need their help today.
帕西蒙！
还是以日耳曼人来替你赢吗？
Still leading with the German?
群众喜欢野蛮人
The crowd love a barbarian.
此外，他让我发财
Besides that, he's making me rich.
努米迪人以前打过吗？
Has that Numidian fought before?
没有，这是第一次
No, first time.
那个呢？苦力还是军人？
And that one? Laborer? Soldier?
西班牙人，以他所能，把他当个阉人吧
He's a Spaniard. He might as well be a
eunuch for what he brings to the ring.
500个罗马币
赌努米迪人及西班牙人合力过关
500 sesterti the Numidian and
Spaniard team makes it through.
一千个赌努米迪人独自过关
And 1,000 that the Numidian
makes it through alone.
你叫我赌自己人输？
Are you asking me to bet against my own man?
太不道德了吧
It's unethical.
涨到2000呢？
What if I make it 2,000?
你们当中有些人，不愿意上场搏斗…
Some of you are thinking you won't fight.
另外一些则是不会搏斗
Some that you can't fight.
大家都喜欢唱高调，除非真正轮到自己上场
Some that you can't fight. They all
say that, until they're out there.
你们听
Listen.
死亡！死亡！
Kill. Kill. Kill.
把刀用力刺进敌人的身体里…
Thrust this into another man's flesh,
观众会为此向你喝采、崇拜你
and then they will applaud
and love you for that.
而你…
你也会开始为了喝采声…
You may begin to love them
而爱上他们
for that.
最终，我们都会化为一堆枯骨
Ultimately, we're all dead men.
可悲的是我们无权选择命运…
Sadly, we cannot choose how,
但有权决定如何面对死亡…
but we can decide how we meet that end,
唯有如此才能像个人一般的…
in order that we are remembered
被人们追忆
as men.
来！
左边的拿盾牌！
On the left, draw your shields.
右边的拿剑
On the right, draw your swords.
死亡！死亡！
Kill, kill, kill...
两人一组，红色跟黄色一起
Pair them up, red with yellow.
下一个！
Next.
快走！
夺权者！
罗马元老与人民
- 滚开！
- 你没有资格统治我们
Go away.
他以凯旋英雄的姿态进入罗马
但他到底征服了什么？
He enters Rome like a conquering
hero, but what has he conquered?
奎格斯，给他时间，他还年轻
Give him time, Gracchus. He's young.
我相信他可以做得很好
I think he could do very well.
替罗马？还是替你？
For Rome or for you?
卢赛斯，去欢迎你母亲，她会很高兴的
Go to your mother, Lucius.
It's what she'd like.
- 卢赛斯
- 母亲
- Lucius.
- Mother.
皇帝万岁
Hail, Caesar.
各位议员们
Senators.
欢迎罗马的新皇帝
Rome greets her new emperor.
您忠心的臣子，向您表示欢迎之意
Your loyal subjects bid
you welcome, Highness.
佛可，谢谢你
Thank you, Falco.
谈到忠心，我想这不用花太多钱吧？
And for the loyal subjects. I
trust they weren't too expensive.
- 我皇
- 奎格斯
- Caesar.
- Gracchus.
罗马为您的归来而欢喜
Rome rejoices in your return, Caesar.
有许多政务需要您处理
There are many matters that
require your attention.
请肃静！肃静
To order. To order.
元老院已经拟订一系列的议程
好方便殿下过目
For your guidance, Caesar, the Senate
has prepared a series of protocols
由市内的相关问题开始…
to begin addressing the
many problems in the city.
首先是希腊区的基础卫生设备…
Beginning with basic sanitation
for the Greek quarter,
设法消灭该区正在蔓延的瘟疫
to combat the plague which is
already springing up there.
所以如果殿下…
So, if Caesar...
奎格斯，你难道不明白
Don't you see, Gracchus?
这才是问题的核心，不是吗？
That's the very problem, isn't it?
我父亲花费毕生的时间
My father spent all his time at study.
研读书本中的知识和哲学
At books and learning and philosophy.
他的晚年尽在阅读元老院的卷轴中度过
He spent his twilight hours
reading scrolls from the Senate.
然而自始至终，他却忽略了人民
And all the while, the people were forgotten.
可是殿下，元老院就代表了人民
But the Senate is the people, sire.
由人民中选出议员，来为民喉舌
Chosen from among the people,
to speak for the people.
奎格斯，我怀疑民众是否像你一样丰衣足食
I doubt many of the people eat
so well as you do, Gracchus.
或是像盖尔斯一样妻妾成群
Or have such splendid mistresses, Gaius.
我自认了解我的人民
I think I understand my own people.
既然如此，根据您个人多方面的经验
Then, perhaps Caesar will
be so good as to teach us.
殿下或许会不吝赐教
Out of his own extensive experience.
我认为是“爱”
I call it love.
我会爱民如子，因为他们是我的子民
I am their father. The
people are my children.
我会将他们紧紧的拥抱在我的胸前
I shall hold them to my
bosom and embrace them.
殿下，您是否拥抱过身染瘟疫的人？
Have you ever embraced
someone dying of plague, sire?
没有，但是如果你再打断我的话…
No, but if you interrupt me again,
我保证你一定会
I assure you that you shall.
议员，我弟弟非常疲倦
Senator, my brother is very tired.
把议程交给我
罗马皇帝应该照人民的意愿行事
Leave your list with me, Caesar
shall do all that Rome requires.
夫人，你总是能以柔克刚，让人不能不服
My lady, as always, your lightest
touch commands obedience.
他们竟敢对我说教？
Who are they to lecture me?
康莫德斯，元老院自有它的效用
Commodus, the Senate has its uses.
有什么用？他们只会耍嘴皮
What uses? All they do is talk.
根本就只需要你和我，还有罗马
It should be just you and me, and Rome.
千万不可以有这种想法
元老院自立国之初便存在着
Don't even think it. There's
always been a Senate.
罗马已经变了
Rome has changed.
有了皇帝就可以治理帝国
It takes an emperor to rule an empire.
- 当然，可是停止人民的…
- 错误观念？
- Of course, but leave the people their...
- Illusions?
传统
Traditions.
我父亲对蛮族发动战争
My father's war against the barbarians...
而他也承认此举毫无意义，但是人民敬爱他
He said it himself, it achieved
nothing, but the people loved him.
人都喜欢胜利的感觉
The people always love victories.
为什么？他们没有目睹战争的残酷
Why? They didn't see the battles.
日耳曼和他们毫不相干
What do they care about Germania?
他们关心罗马的富强
They care about the greatness of Rome.
“罗马的富强”
The greatness of Rome.
那到底是什么？
Well, what is that?
是一种理念
It's an idea. Greatness.
- 富强是一个憧憬
- 没错，一个憧憬
- Greatness is a vision.
- Exactly. A vision.
你没发现吗？露西拉
Do you not see, Lucilla?
我会给人民一个罗马的新憧憬
他们也将为此而敬爱我
I will give the people a vision of
Rome, and they'll love me for it.
他们很快就会忘记那几个爱说教的老头子
And they'll soon forget the tedious
sermonizing of a few dry, old men.
我会给罗马人民一个前所未有的憧憬
I will give the people the
greatest vision of their lives.
“角斗士，肉搏实战”
红酒、白酒任君畅饮！
White and red wine for
your drinking pleasure.
竞技
Games.
一百五十天的竞技活动
150 days of games.
他比我想像的还要聪明
He's cleverer than I thought.
聪明？要不是因为害怕他的御卫队…
Clever. The whole of Rome
would be laughing at him,
全罗马的人都会嘲笑他
if they weren't so afraid of his Praetorians.
害怕跟好奇，强而有力的组合
Fear and wonder, a powerful combination.
你真的认为民众会被他的手段所瞒骗？
You really think the people are
going to be seduced by that?
我认为他了解罗马的本质，群众代表了罗马
I think he knows what
Rome is. Rome is the mob.
对他们变魔术，就可以分散他们的注意力
He'll conjure magic for them,
and they'll be distracted.
拿走他们的自由，他们还会哄堂大笑
He'll take away their freedom
and still they'll roar.
维系罗马脉动的不是元老院的大理石地砖
The beating heart of Rome is
not the marble of the Senate.
而是竞技场内的沙地
It's the sand of the Colosseum.
他替人民带来死亡…
He'll bring them death,
民众却为此敬爱他
And they will love him for it.
Spaniard.
你就只懂得杀死他们
All you do is kill, kill, kill.
群众不喜欢一个屠夫，他们要个英雄
The crowd don't want a
butcher, they want a hero.
我们还要他们回来看戏呢
You want them to keep coming back,
别光杀死他们，别忘了你是个艺人
so don't just hack them to pieces.
Remember, you are an entertainer.
西班牙人
Spaniard.
做场好戏吧！
So entertain.
你们还不满意吗？
Are you not entertained?
这不就是你们来这里的原因吗？
Is this not why you are here?
西班牙人！西班牙人！
Spaniard.
你想要什么？
What do you want?
女人？
Girl?
男人？
Boy?
- 你找我有事
- 没错，是有事
- You sent for me?
- Yes, I did.
西班牙人，你的确很棒，但你不是最厉害的
You're good, Spaniard, but
you're not that good.
你可以变得更优秀
You could be magnificent.
我杀人是因为别人的要求，这样就够了
I'm required to kill, so
I kill. That is enough.
乡下地方或许可以，但在罗马却行不通
That's enough for the
provinces, but not for Rome.
年轻的皇帝安排了一系列的展示
The young emperor has arranged
a series of spectacles
来纪念他的父亲，马卡斯奥里勒斯
to commemorate his father, Marcus Aurelius.
我觉得很好笑…
I find that amusing,
因为是马卡斯奥里勒斯…
since it was Marcus Aurelius,
博学、无所不知的奥里勒斯停止了搏斗竞技
the wise, the all-knowing Marcus
Aurelius, that closed us down.
好不容易，经过五年…
So, finally, after five years
of scratching a living in
在这个跳蚤为患的村庄讨生活的日子
flea-infested villages,
我们终于要回到属于我们的地方…
we're finally going back to where we belong.
罗马竞技场
The Colosseum.
西班牙人，你应该去看竞技场
You should see the Colosseum, Spaniard.
五万名罗马群众…
50,000 Romans
注视你斗剑时的每个动作
watching every movement of your sword.
期待你挥出致命的一击
Willing you to make that killer blow.
在你挥剑之前的寂静和那之后的骚动
The silence before you strike,
and the noise afterwards,
喧闹声不断提高…
it rises... rises up like...
像是暴风雨
like a storm.
而你自己就是雷神
As if you were the thunder god himself.
- 你以前是角斗士？
- 对，我是
- You were a gladiator?
- Yes, I was.
你赢得你的自由？
You won your freedom?
很久以前，有一位皇帝…
A long time ago, the Emperor...
送给我一把剑
presented me with a rudius.
那只是一把木剑
It's just a wooden sword.
你得到自由的象征
A symbol of your freedom.
他用木剑点了我的肩，我便获得了自由
He touched me on the
shoulder, and I was free.
你认识马卡斯奥里勒斯？
You knew Marcus Aurelius?
我没有说我认识他，我说他曾经碰过我的肩
I did not say I knew him. I said he
touched me on the shoulder once.
你问我到底想要什么
You asked me what I want.
我也希望站在皇帝的面前…
I, too, want to stand in
front of the Emperor.
就像你一样
As you did.
那你就听我的，向我学习
Then listen to me. Learn from me.
我是最棒的角斗士，不是因为我杀人迅速
I wasn't the best because I killed quickly.
我之所以最棒是因为群众崇拜我
I was the best because the crowd loved me.
赢取群众的心就能赢得你的自由
Win the crowd, and you'll win your freedom.
我会赢得群众的心
I will win the crowd.
我将带给他们一场从未见过的表演
I will give them something
they have never seen before.
那么西班牙人，我们将一起前往罗马…
So, Spaniard, we shall go to Rome together
展开一趟血腥的冒险
and have bloody adventures.
群众会让我们的荷包鼓胀…
And the great whore will suckle us
开心得合不拢嘴
until we are fat and happy
and can suckle no more.
然后…
And then,
当死的人够多了…
when enough men have died,
或许你可以得到你的自由
perhaps you will have your freedom.
拿去，这个给你
Here. Use this.
在远处的某个地方有我的国家
It's somewhere out there, my country,
跟我的家
My home.
我的妻子正在准备食物
My wife is preparing food.
我的女儿从河边打水回来
My daughters carry water from the river.
我能再见到他们吗？
Will I ever see them again?
我认为不可能
I think no.
你相信死后能再见到他们吗？
Do you believe you'll see
them again when you die?
我相信
I think so.
只不过我会比他们先死
But then, I will die soon.
他们会再活好几年
They will not die for many years.
我必须等他们
I'll have to wait.
但你愿意等？
But you would wait.
当然
Of course.
你知道…
You see,
我的妻子…
My wife
还有我的儿子已经在等我了
and my son, are already waiting for me.
你会和他们相聚的
You'll meet them again.
只是时候未到
But not yet.
时候未到
Not yet.
- 除非…
- 时候未到
- Unless...
- Not yet.
时候未到
Not yet.
I see him.
他在那里
- Where?
- There he is.
出来
Out.
快一点！快出来
Move. Out.
Are there any others?
老朋友，真高兴再见到你
Good to see you again, old friend.
带给我财富
Bring me fortune.
你看过这么壮观的建筑物吗？
Have you ever seen anything like that before?
我不知道他们是如何办到的
I didn't know men could build such things.
赢取观众的心
Win the crowd.
进去！走啊！
Get Inside. Move.
进去
Inside.
他睡得好香，因为他备受宠爱
He sleeps so well because he's loved.
来吧！弟弟，已经很晚了
Come, Brother. It's late.
我会让罗马成为当代的奇迹
I will make Rome the wonder of the ages.
奎格斯和他的朋友一点都不明白
That is what Gracchus and his
friends don't understand.
我的欲望在脑海中起伏，让我头痛欲裂
All my desires are
splitting my head to pieces.
康莫德斯，把苏打水喝下去
Commodus, drink this tonic.
我认为时机已经成熟
I think the time is almost right.
我可以在悼念父亲的庆典上…
I could announce the
dissolution of the Senate
宣布解散元老院
at the celebration to honor our father.
你觉得我该这么做吗？
You think I should?
人民能接受吗？
Are the people ready?
我认为你该休息了
I think you need your rest now.
你会不会留下来陪我？
Will you stay with me?
弟弟，你还是怕黑吗？
Still afraid of the dark, Brother?
是的
Still?
永远都怕
Always.
- 今晚留下来陪我
- 你知道不可能
- Stay with me tonight?
- You know I won't.
那么吻我
Then kiss me.
晚安，我的弟弟
Sleep, Brother.
用聋子跟瞎了的佣人…
Having servants who are deaf and mute
至少让我活得久一点
at least ensures I live a little longer.
他们现在正在抓那些学者
They're arresting scholars now.
只要有谁敢开口，即使是讽刺诗作者、纪录者
Anyone who dares speak out.
Even satirists and chroniclers.
或是数学家
And mathematicians.
都全送到竞技场去送死
And all to feed the arena.
元老不赞成军事管制法
The Senate did not approve martial law.
御卫队是恐怖统治的根源
This reign of terror is
entirely the Praetorians'.
我晚上就不敢出门
I'm afraid to go out after dark.
你应该对你白天做的事感到恐惧才是
You should be more afraid of
your activities during the day.
元老院里布满了婊子老大佛可带领的奸细
The Senate is full of his spies.
Led by that whoremaster, Falco.
但我总想弄清楚，他到底在想什么？
But what is in his mind? That's
what I trouble myself with.
他把他的时间都花在…
He spends all his days singularly obsessed,
推崇你爸爸的节目上
planning the festival to honor your father.
他甚至忽略了政府最基本的事
He neglects even the most
fundamental task of government.
那他到底在计划什么？
So just what is he planning?
那代价是什么呢？
And what pays for it?
竞技活动花很多钱，而我们也没有徵新税
These daily games are costing a
fortune, yet we have no new taxes.
我们的未来
The future.
未来会让一切都值得的
The future pays for it.
他已经开始卖储存的谷物了
He's started selling the grain reserves.
不会吧
This can't be true.
他正在卖罗马储存的谷物
He is selling Rome's reserves of grain.
人民再过两年就得挨饿
The people will be starving in two years.
希望人民能享受这游戏
I hope they enjoy the games.
因为过不多久，他们就会为了这竞技游戏而死
Soon enough, they will
be dead because of them.
- 罗马人一定要知道真相
- 怎么做呢？
- Rome must know this.
- And how?
他想要解散元老院
He's going to dissolve the Senate.
有谁能及早告诉他们呢？你吗？奎格斯
And who will tell them before
it's too late? You, Gracchus?
你，盖尔斯
You, Gaius?
你会在元老院前弹劾我弟弟吗？
Will you make a speech on the floor
of the Senate denouncing my brother?
然后看着你家人在竞技场上被杀？
And then see your family in the Colosseum?
谁敢呢？
Who'd dare?
因为我儿子是王位的继承人…
I have been living in a
prison of fear every day
所以我每天过得心惊胆跳
because my son is heir to the throne.
他一定得死
He must die.
昆塔斯和御卫队会趁机掌权的
Quintus and the Praetorians would
simply seize control for themselves.
不会的，群龙无首也成不了大器
No. Cut off the head and
the snake cannot strike.
露西拉，盖尔斯说得没错
Lucilla, Gaius is right.
直到我们制服御卫队前，我们什么也做不成
Until we can neutralize the
Praetorians, we can achieve nothing.
那就什么都不做？
So we do nothing?
不，我们按兵不动
No, child. We keep our counsel.
养精蓄锐
We prepare.
只要他得人心，我们就治不了他
As long as the people support
him, we are voices without steel.
英雄无用武之地
We are air.
但照他每天树敌的速度来看
But with every day that
passes, he makes enemies.
总有一天，他的敌人会多过朋友
One day, he'll have more
enemies than friends.
等到那天我们就动手
And on that day, we will act.
他们会回手
Then we will strike.
但到时候…
But until then,
我们会很温顺
we are docile.
会听话
We are obedient.
也更是变化莫测的
And we are treacherous.
来！
Come on. Get out of the way.
Pick me.
I want to cover you in kisses.
好了！够了
All right, that's enough.
皇帝想看搏斗，不表示我就得牺牲最好的战士
The emperor wants battles. I don't
want to sacrifice my best fighters.
群众想看竞技，所以皇帝举办大型搏斗
The crowd wants battles, so
the Emperor gives them battles.
- 你则得到迦太基的战役
- 迦太基的屠杀
- And you get the battle of Carthage.
- The massacre of Carthage.
你为什么不把监狱里的乞丐、小偷都找来？
Why not go down to the prison and
round up all the beggars and thieves?
早就找了
We've done that.
你如果想要我放弃全帝国中最棒的角斗士…
If you want to give away the best
gladiators in the whole of the Empire,
我就得收双倍的价钱
I want double the rates.
我们不是按照合约付你钱就是取消合约
You'll get your contract rates, or
you'll get your contract cancelled.
不高兴的话…
You don't like it?
你可以滚回你的老家去
Then you can crawl back down that
shithole that you came from.
等一等！卡西亚斯
Cassius, please. Please, Cassius.
你就是外号“西班牙人”的角斗士？
Gladiator, are you the one
they call the Spaniard?
对
Yes.
大家都说你是巨人
They said you were a giant.
单手就能捏碎大人的头！
They said you could crush a
man's skull with one hand.
大人？不可能
A man's? No.
小孩的头
A boy's.
- 西班牙有没有优良的马？
- 有最优良的马
- They have good horses in Spain?
- Some of the best.
这是银子
This is Argento, and this is Scarto.
它们是我的马
They were my horses.
可是被别人抢走了
They were taken from me.
西班牙人，我喜欢你，我会替你加油
I like you, Spaniard. I shall cheer for you.
- 他们准你看竞技比赛？
- 我舅舅说会让我变得勇敢
- They let you watch the games?
- My uncle says it makes me strong.
- 那你父亲怎么说？
- 我父亲已经去世了
- What does your father say?
- My father's dead.
卢赛斯少爷，该回家了
Master Lucius, it is time.
我得走了
I have to go.
你叫卢赛斯？
Your name is Lucius?
卢赛斯维勒斯，为了纪念我父亲
Lucius Verus, after my father.
往下放！
Lower.
克狄亚斯！
Claudius.
- 什么事？
- 拿多点盾牌来！
- Yes, sir?
- More shields.
是
等到皇帝入场后，举起你们的武器敬礼…
When the Emperor enters,
raise your weapons, salute him
然后齐声向他问候
and then speak together.
面对着皇帝，不可以背对着他
Face the Emperor and don't
turn your back on him.
去吧！为了荣誉而战
Go, and die with honor.
欢迎伟大的皇帝！
Hail, mighty Caesar.
皇帝万岁！皇帝万岁！
角斗士们向您致敬！
We who are about to die salute you.
今天…
On this day,
我们把战场移到神圣的古代…
we reach back to hallowed antiquity,
呈现在各位面前的是…
to bring you a recreation of the second fall
迦太基沦亡的历史战役！
of mighty Carthage.
在荒芜的札玛平原…
On the barren plain of Zama,
汉尼拔将军的常胜军…
there stood the invincible armies
严阵以待
of the barbarian, Hannibal.
来自所有残暴民族的佣兵和战士…
Ferocious mercenaries and warriors
毫不留情的…
from all brute nations,
破坏…
bent on merciless destruction,
征服
conquest.
很荣幸为各位介绍…
Your Emperor is pleased to give you
野蛮的异邦人！
the barbarian horde.
这里有谁打过仗？
Anyone here been in the army?
我！我在泛度巴纳跟你一同服役
Yes. I served with you at Vindobona.
你可以帮我忙
You can help me.
不管从铁门后面会出现什么…
Whatever comes out of these gates,
我们只有同心协力才会有较大的胜算
we've got a better chance of
survival if we work together.
明白吗？
Do you understand?
只要团结一致，我们就能活命
If we stay together, we survive.
很荣幸为您介绍，非洲的希比欧军团…
I'm pleased to bring you the legionnaires of
奋战到底！
Scipio Africanus.
死亡！
To the death.
靠拢！
Stay close.
集合！
Come together.
纵队交错排列！
Staggered columns.
你的人死定了
- Soon all your men will be slain.
- You don't have a chance.
固定盾牌，紧密衔接
- Lock your shields. Stay as one.
- As one.
稳住！
Hold.
Hold. As one.
锁住盾牌
Well done.
稳住！
Hold. Diamond.
做得好！
贺格！
Haken.
一队去移战车，一队跟我来！
This column to the chariots.
This column stay with me.
动作快！
Quickly.
- 去前面
- 快点！
- Get out there.
- Hurry.
麦希穆斯！
Maximus.
单排队形！单排队形！
Single column.
我们赢了！
We win.
卡西亚斯，我的历史不太好
My history's a little hazy, Cassius.
不过，输了迦太基战役的应该是异邦人吧？
But shouldn't the barbarians
lose the battle of Carthage?
是的，殿下
Yes, sire.
殿下，请见谅
Forgive me, sire.
没关系，我喜欢惊喜
No, I rather enjoy surprises.
他是谁？
Who is he?
殿下，大家都叫他“西班牙人”
They call him the Spaniard, sire.
我打算和他会面
I think I'll meet him.
好的，殿下
Yes, sire.
为异邦人欢呼！
Hail to the barbarians.
前进！严密戒备！
Forward.
放下你们的武器
Drop your weapons.
角斗士，皇帝要见你
Gladiator, the Emperor has asked for you.
随时听候差遣
I'm at the Emperor's service.
起身，起身
Rise.
西班牙人，你果然名不虚传
Your fame is well deserved, Spaniard.
我相信其他的角斗士都不是你的对手
I don't think there's ever
been a gladiator to match you.
这位年轻人坚持你是英雄转世
This young man insists you are Hector reborn.
还是你是天神的化身？
Or was it Hercules?
英雄为何不表明身份
告诉大家你的真实姓名？
Why doesn't the hero reveal himself
and tell us all your real name?
你总有名字吧？
You do have a name?
“角斗士”就是我的名字
My name is Gladiator.
你好大胆，竟然背对着我，奴隶！
How dare you show your back to me? Slave.
脱掉你的头盔，告诉我你的名字
You will remove your helmet
and tell me your name.
我叫麦希穆斯…
My name is Maximus Decimus Meridius,
北方军队的指挥官…
commander of the armies of the north,
菲力克斯军团的将军…
general of the Felix Legions.
合法皇帝马卡斯奥里勒斯忠心的仆人…
Loyal servant to the true
emperor, Marcus Aurelius.
儿子被人谋杀…
Father to a murdered son,
妻子遭人杀害…
husband to a murdered wife,
不管今生或者来世，我定会替他们报仇
and I will have my vengeance,
in this life or the next.
士兵！
Arms.
胜者生存！
Live. Live. Live.
卫兵，停手！
Arms at rest.
麦希穆斯！麦希穆斯！
Maximus! Maximus! Maximus!
父亲
Father.
为什么他还活着？
Why is he still alive?
我不知道
I don't know.
他应该早就死了
He shouldn't be alive.
实在让人生气
It vexes me.
我非常的生气
I'm terribly vexed.
我不得不这么安排
I did what I had to do.
要是按照父亲的意思，罗马帝国早就解体了
If Father had had his way, the
Empire would have been torn apart.
你一定明白的，对吗？
You do see that?
对
Yes.
你看到他的时候有什么感觉？
What did you feel when you saw him?
没有任何感觉
I felt nothing.
他伤你很深，对不对？
He wounded you deeply, didn't he?
是我伤害他比较多
No more than I wounded him.
在日耳曼的时候他们说谎
They lied to me in Germania.
跟我说他已经死了
They told me he was dead.
他们骗我，表示他们不尊敬我
If they lie to me, they don't respect me.
如果他们不尊敬我，又怎么可能爱我呢？
If they don't respect me,
how can they ever love me?
那么你必须让军团了解…
Then you must let the legions know
他们的背叛行为一定会受到惩罚
their treachery will not go unpunished.
可怜的姐姐
Poor sister,
我绝对不想与你为敌
I wouldn't want to be your enemy.
你打算怎么做？
What will you do?
出来
This way.
贵妇人付高价是为了让英勇的角斗士取悦她
Rich matrons pay well to be
pleasured by the bravest champions.
我晓得你弟弟会派刺客
I knew your brother would send assassins.
可是我没想到他会派自己的御卫队
I didn't realize he would send his best.
麦希穆斯，他毫不知情
Maximus, he doesn't know.
我的家人被钉在十字架上活活烧死
My family was burned and crucified
while they were still alive.
- 我真的不知道…
- 别对我说谎
- I knew nothing.
- Don't lie to me.
我为他们流泪
I wept for them.
就像你为你父亲哭泣一样？
As you wept for your father?
自从我父亲去世以后，我便生活在恐惧之中
I have been living in a prison
of fear since that day.
无法哀悼自己的父亲，只因为害怕自己的弟弟
To be unable to mourn your
father for fear of your brother.
时时刻刻都生活在恐惧之中…
To live in terror every moment of every day,
因为自己的儿子也是王位继承人
because your son is heir to the throne.
我为此而流泪
I have wept.
我儿子是无辜的
My son was innocent.
我儿子也是
So is mine.
难道非得用我儿子的命来换取你的信任？
Must my son die, too,
before you will trust me?
我相不相信你又有何区别？
What does it matter if I trust you or not?
你难道不明白诸神已经赦免了你？
The gods have spared you.
Don't you understand?
我今天看到比罗马皇帝还要有权利的奴隶
Today I saw a slave become more
powerful than the Emperor of Rome.
诸神已经赦免了我？
The gods have spared me?
因为他们的怜悯，我才有娱乐群众的力量
I am at their mercy, with the
power only to amuse a mob.
那是力量
That is power.
群众代表罗马
The mob is Rome.
康莫德斯控制他们才能掌控一切
While Commodus controls
them, he controls everything.
听我说
Listen to me.
我弟弟绝大部分的敌人都在元老院
My brother has enemies,
most of all in the Senate.
只是当人民支持他的时候…
But while the people follow him,
除了你，没有人敢跟他正面冲突
no one would dare stand up to him until you.
他们反对他却动口不动手
They oppose him, yet they do nothing.
有些政治家为罗马奉献出全部的心力
There are some politicians who have
dedicated their lives to Rome.
他们之中的领袖
One man above all.
如果我出面安排，你会愿意和他见面吗？
If I can arrange it, will you meet him?
你到底明不明白？
Do you not understand?
我只是个奴隶，随时随地都有可能丧命！
I may die in this cell tonight, or
in the arena tomorrow. I am a slave.
我又能改变什么？
What possible difference can I make?
这个人跟你有着相同的目的
This man wants what you want.
那让他去杀了康莫德斯！
Then have him kill Commodus.
我曾经认识一个人…
I knew a man once,
一个高尚的人
a noble man,
他不但有原则而且敬爱我的父亲…
a man of principle, who loved my father.
我父亲也爱他
And my father loved him.
这个人为罗马贡献良多
This man served Rome well.
那个人已经死了
That man is gone.
你弟弟的计划非常成功
Your brother did his work well.
让我帮你
Let me help you.
好，你可以帮我
Yes, you can help me.
忘了我们曾经认识，再也不要过来看我
Forget you ever knew me,
and never come here again.
卫兵，夫人要离开了
Guard. The lady has finished with me.
你叫什么名字？
What's your name?
克拉斯
Julian Crassus.
名字？
Name?
马卡斯，先生
Marcus, sire.
我父亲的名字
My father's name.
他们在发现那四个人的尸体时
一定就知道麦希穆斯逃了
They must have known of Maximus' escape
when they found the bodies of the four men.
他们一定以为是蛮族干的
They thought it was a barbarian raid.
他们是好人啊，对您忠心不二
These are good men, sire.
Loyal to the Emperor.
拉弓！
Load arrows.
准备放剑！
Prepare to fire.
或许你早就知道…
Then perhaps it was you who knew.
而从未告诉我
And never told me.
- 我不知情
- 你不知情？
- I didn't know.
- You didn't know?
将军总是控制大局的人
But a general is always in control.
总是下军令的，不是吗？
Always in command, isn't he?
是的，大帝
Yes, Caesar.
那就下军令吧，下啊
Then give the command. Say it.
放剑
Fire.
麦希穆斯
Maximus?
你指挥过军团？赢过无数的战役？
You commanded legions?
You had many victories?
- 是的
- 在日耳曼？
- Yes.
- In Germania?
在许多国家
In many countries.
将军
General.
你有一个了不起的名字
You have a great name.
在除掉你之前，他必先羞辱你的名声
He must kill your name before he kills you.
是的，在最旁边
Yes, at the far end.
- 盖尔斯议员
- 你好
- Senator Gaius.
- Hello.
奎格斯议员
Senator Gracchus.
很难得看到你出现在这种龙蛇杂处的地方
Don't often see you enjoying the
pleasures of the vulgar crowd.
我不会假装跟民众打成一片…
I don't pretend to be a
man of the people, Senator.
但我会尽到为民喉舌的责任
But I do try to be a man for the people.
皇帝万岁！皇帝万岁！
Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
罗马的人民！
People of Rome.
今天是安提阿战役的第四日…
On the fourth day of Antioch,
同时也是竞技庆典的第64天
we can celebrate the 64th day of the games.
在他宽大的德政下…
And, in his majestic charity,
皇帝决定赐予罗马人民…
the Emperor has deigned this day
to favor the people of Rome
一场历史性的决赛
with an historical final match.
退休五年后重回竞技场…
Returning to the Colosseum today
after five years in retirement,
很高兴为各位请到…
Caesar is pleased to bring you
罗马历史上…
the only undefeated champion
唯一的常胜冠军
in Roman history,
他是来自高卢传奇的底格里斯
the legendary Tigris of Gaul.
他太清楚该如何操纵群众
He knows too well how to manipulate the mob.
马卡斯奥里勒斯的梦想，是建立一个新的罗马
Marcus Aurelius had a dream
that was Rome, Proximo.
但新罗马不应该是这样的
This is not it.
奥里勒斯已经死了
Marcus Aurelius is dead, Maximus.
我们只是凡夫俗子，一切终归尘土
We mortals are but shadows and dust.
麦希穆斯，一切终归尘土
Shadows and dust.
代表帕西蒙训练会馆…
Representing the training
lyceum of Antonius Proximo,
让我们郑重介绍…
Caesar is proud to give you
麦希穆斯！
Aelius Maximus.
他们把他当成自己人，敞开双臂欢迎他
They embrace him like he's one of their own.
弟弟，群众是很善变的
不出一个月就会忘记了
The mob is fickle, Brother.
He'll be forgotten in a month.
错了，用不着那么久
No, much sooner than that.
全都安排好了
It's been arranged.
Maximus! Maximus! Maximus!
角斗士向您致敬
We who are about to die salute you.
麦希穆斯，我们支持你！
We're with you, Maximus.
打败他！
Come on, finish him.
用力拉！
放开！放开！
Loose. Loose.
- 砍他！
- 死亡！
- Get him.
- Kill him.
死亡！死亡！
Kill.
仁慈的麦希穆斯！
Maximus the Merciful.
麦希穆斯！麦希穆斯！
Maximus! Maximus! Maximus!
卫兵！前进，成攻击队形
Forward, guards. On battery.
我该拿你怎么办？
What am I going to do with you?
为什么你不去死
You simply won't die.
我们之间的差异真有这么大吗？
Are we so different, you and I?
必要时，你也会杀人，就像我一样
You take life when you have to, as I do.
只剩下一个人我非杀不可，我的责任就完成了
I have only one more life
to take. Then it is done.
那就动手啊！
Then take it now.
他们告诉我，你儿子…
They tell me your son
在被钉上十字架的时候，像女孩子一样在尖叫
squealed like a girl when
they nailed him to the cross.
至于你太太…
And your wife
在被他们蹂躏的时候…
moaned like a whore
像妓女一样在呻吟，一次又一次…
when they ravaged her again and again
在呻吟
and again.
您呼风唤雨的日子，就快要结束了…
The time for honoring yourself
will soon be at an end.
殿下
Highness.
Maximus! Maximus! Maximus!
将军！
General.
Get back.
- 将军！
- 西斯洛！
- General.
- Cicero.
General.
- 你在哪扎营？
- 在奥斯亚
- Where are you camped?
- Ostia.
- 麦希穆斯，我们爱你
- 赞美胜利者
- We love you, Maximus.
- Praise the victor.
告诉大家我还活着，来找我
Tell the men their general lives. Find me.
- 快去
- 来找我
- Move along.
- Find me.
他们可以听到你祈祷吗？
Can they hear you?
- 谁？
- 你在黄泉的家人
- Who?
- Your family, in the afterlife.
- 当然可以
- 你跟他们说什么？
- Oh, yes.
- What do you say to them?
对我的儿子…
To my boy,
我告诉他，我们很快就会见面了…
I tell him I will see him again soon.
骑马的时候，记得脚跟要压低
To keep his heels down when
he's riding his horse.
对我的妻子…
To my wife...
那不关你的事
That is not your business.
现在群众反而敬爱他的仁慈
And now they love Maximus for his mercy.
所以我更不能杀他，因为那会显得我残暴
So I can't just kill him, or it
makes me even more unmerciful.
这整件事简直就像个恶梦
The whole thing's like some crazed nightmare.
他是在公然向你挑战
He is defying you.
他每一次的胜利，都是一种反抗的举动
His every victory is an act of defiance.
群众和元老院议员都看到了
The mob sees this, and so do the Senate.
只要有他在的一天，他们就会越来越大胆
Every day he lives, they grow bolder.
- 杀了他
- 不行
- Kill him.
- No.
我不会帮他成为烈士
I will not make a martyr of him.
我今天到元老院…
When I went to the Senate today,
特地叫他们拿储存的谷物来付竞技赛的钱
I purposely told them about using the
grain reserves to pay for the games.
你知道接下来发生什么事吗？
And did you note what happened?
- 没事
- 没错，什么都没发生
- Nothing.
- Exactly. Nothing.
没有一个人反对
Not a single word of protest.
连粗野的奎格斯也不出声
Even the insolent senator
Gracchus was silent as a mouse.
为什么？
Why?
有人告诉我，某种海蛇…
I have been told of a certain sea snake
用非常特别的方法来引诱猎物
which has a very unusual
method of attracting its prey.
它会假装受伤，躺在海底
It will lie at the bottom of
the ocean, as if wounded.
然后它的敌人会渐渐的靠近…
Then its enemies will approach,
可是它会继续躺着不动
and yet it will lie quite still.
接着敌人开始慢慢的咬它…
And then its enemies will
take little bites of it,
但它还是保持不动
and yet it remains still.
所以…
So,
我们要不动声色…
we will lie still,
耐心等我们的敌人上钩
and let our enemies come to us and nibble.
让元老院跟着自投罗网
Have every senator followed.
西斯洛，我的老朋友，我以为再也见不到你了
Cicero, my old friend. I thought perhaps
I'd seen you for the last time.
- 我以为你死了
- 差不多
- I thought you were dead.
- Close.
- 军团在奥斯亚扎营多久了？
- 整个冬季
- How long have the men been in Ostia?
- All winter.
- 他们的状况如何？
- 又胖又无聊
- And how do they look?
- Fat and bored.
- 指挥官是谁？
- 从罗马来的白痴
- Who's in command?
- Some fool from Rome.
他们最快要什么时候才能准备好？
How soon could they be ready to fight?
为了你，明天
For you, tomorrow.
有件事我需要你帮忙
I need you to do something for me.
各位，快来看
Come see. Witness.
没去竞技场没关系
If you haven't been in the arena,
you can see the show here.
康莫德斯皇帝快被巨人麦希穆斯打败了
Giant Maximus is defeating
our Emperor Commodus.
我们该怎么办？他打败每一个人…
What are we to do? He's defying everyone.
我们这么对他，他们
Why are you doing this?
我的天！
- 他赢了
- 让路！让路
- He got him!
- Give way! Give way!
Three casks of red wine.
夫人，我在泛度巴纳服侍过你父亲
My lady? I served your father at Vindobona.
- 走开！
- 夫人
- Back.
- My lady.
我在泛度巴纳服侍过你父亲
I served your father at Vindobona.
走开！
Back!
我也服侍过麦希穆斯将军，我还在服侍他
And I served the General
Maximus, I serve him still.
停下来！停
- Stop. Stop.
- Stop!
退下
Stand back.
将军带话给你，他愿意见你的政治家
The General sends word. He
will meet your politician.
- 士兵，奖赏你的忠心
- 夫人，谢谢你
- For your loyalty, soldier.
- Thank you, my lady.
Hup!
让我们独处
Leave us.
奎格斯议员
Senator Gracchus.
将军
General.
希望今天我来这里能够证明…
I hope my coming here today
is evidence enough that
你可以相信我
you can trust me.
- 元老院跟你的立场一致？
- 元老院？
- The Senate is with you?
- The Senate?
是的，我代表他们
Yes. I can speak for them.
你能换取我的自由、偷偷把我运出罗马吗？
You can buy my freedom and
smuggle me out of Rome?
去哪里？
To what end?
把我送到城墙外
Get me outside the city walls.
准备好马匹让我去奥斯亚，我的军队在那扎营
Have fresh horses ready to take me
to Ostia. My army is encamped there.
我会在第二天傍晚率领五千名士兵回来
By nightfall of the second day, I
shall return at the head of 5,000 men.
但是军团的新指挥官…
But the legions all have new commanders
全都效忠康莫德斯
loyal to Commodus.
只要我的部下看到我还活着
你就知道他们效忠谁了
Let my men see me alive, and you
shall see where their loyalties lie.
简直是疯了
This is madness.
数百年来，罗马军队没有进过首都
No Roman army has entered the
capital in a hundred years.
我不愿意引狼入室
I will not trade one
dictatorship for another!
议员，商量权宜办法的时间已经过了
The time for half-measures
and talk is over, Senator.
在你光荣的政变之后，又将如何？
And after your glorious coup, what then?
你会带着五千名士兵离开
You'll take your 5,000 warriors and leave?
我会离开
I will leave.
士兵会留下来保护你受元老院的指挥
The soldiers will stay for your protection,
under the command of the Senate.
换言之…
So,
一旦罗马是你的，你会立刻将它交还给人民？
once all of Rome is yours, you'll
just give it back to the people?
告诉我原因
Tell me why.
因为那是某人死前最后的愿望
Because that was the last
wish of a dying man.
我会杀了康莫德斯
I will kill Commodus.
罗马的命运就交给你了
The fate of Rome I leave to you.
马卡斯奥里勒斯信任你
Marcus Aurelius trusted you.
他的女儿信任你
His daughter trusts you.
我愿意相信你
I will trust you.
目前的时间紧迫
But we have little time.
给我两天的时间…
Give me two days,
我会想办法把你弄出去
and I will buy your freedom.
至于你…
And you...
你千万不能有事
You stay alive.
否则我就完了
Or I'll be dead.
我们得走了
Now we must go.
他会在竞技场等你
He'll be waiting for you. Stand
at the foot of the Colossus.
他会找到你的
He'll find you.
不可能成功的
It won't work.
皇帝对一切t如指掌
The Emperor knows too much.
对我来说…
And as for me,
情势越来越危险
it's becoming dangerous.
我回来时会酬谢你
You will be paid on my return.
我向你保证
I give you my word.
保证？你不回来怎么办？
Your word? What if you don't return?
帕西蒙，你还记得信任别人的感觉吗？
Do you remember what it
was to have trust, Proximo?
信任？
Trust?
有谁值得我信任？
Who am I to trust?
- 我会杀了康莫德斯
- 对我有什么好处？
- I will kill Commodus.
- Why would I want that?
我靠他发财
He makes me rich.
将军，我知道你是个信守承诺的人
I know that you are a man
of your word, General.
我也知道你愿意为荣誉而死
I know that you would die for honor.
愿意为罗马牺牲
You would die for Rome.
愿意为祖先的名誉而死
You would die for the
memory of your ancestors.
可是我，换个角度来说…
But I, on the other hand,
我不过是个表演艺人
I'm an entertainer.
卫兵！
Guard!
他杀了还你自由的那个人
He killed the man who set you free.
大人，是御卫队
Praetorians, master.
停！
Halt!
你去哪了？
Where have you been?
我派人去找你
I sent for you.
弟弟，别小题大做
Please, Brother.
什么事让你烦心？
What's troubling you?
是不是奎格斯有了新爱人
Does Gracchus have a new lover?
我不知道
I don't know.
我以为你和他见过面
I thought you'd seen him.
他像伤寒一样影响每个人
He infects everyone like a putrid fever.
为了罗马着想，必须要牺牲元老院
For the health of Rome,
the Senate must be bled.
奎格斯也不能幸免
And he will bleed, too.
时机成熟了
Very soon.
不要选在今晚
But not tonight.
记得父亲曾说过的话吗？
Do you remember what our father said once?
“一场梦…”
"It's a dream,
“生命就是…”
a frightful dream,
“一场可怕的梦”
life is."
你认为他说的是不是真的？
Do you think that's true?
我不知道
I don't know.
我认为是真的
I think it is.
而我只能和你分享
And I have only you to share it with.
张开你的嘴
Open your mouth.
你知道我爱你
You know I love you.
我也爱你
And I love you.
出去！滚出去！
Out. Get out!
快点！
Move!
将军，恭喜你！
Congratulations, General.
你的朋友非常有说服力
You've got very persuasive friends.
我弟弟已经逮捕了奎格斯
My brother's had Gracchus arrested.
我们不能再等下去，今天晚上一定要走
We daren't wait any longer.
We must leave tonight.
帕西蒙半夜会来把你带到大门口
Proximo will come at midnight
and take you to the gate.
你的仆人，西斯洛会骑着马在那边等你
Your servant, Cicero, will be
waiting there with horses.
- 你一个人独力安排这一切
- 对
- You have done all this?
- Yes.
你冒的风险太大了
You risk too much.
我有太多的债需要偿还
I have much to pay for.
你并没有亏欠任何人
You have nothing to pay for.
你爱你儿子，为了他，你变得十分坚强
You love your son. You are strong for him.
我觉得好累
I am tired of being strong.
我弟弟憎恨全世界，尤其是你
My brother hates all the
world, and you most of all.
- 因为你父亲选择我
- 不
- Because your father chose me?
- No.
因为我父亲爱你
Because my father loved you.
因为我也爱你
And because I loved you.
在很久以前
A long time ago.
我变了很多吗？
Was I very different then?
你以前比较爱笑
You laughed more.
我一直都觉得很寂寞…
I have felt alone all my life.
除了跟你在一起的时候
Except with you.
我该走了
I must go.
是的
Yes.
这里，那里
There. There.
我赢了
And I've got you.
- 现在玩士兵打仗不会太晚吗？
- 我不是罗马士兵
- Isn't it late to be playing legionnaire?
- I'm not a legionnaire.
- 不是罗马士兵？
- 我是角斗士
- Not a legionnaire?
- I'm a gladiator.
角斗士？
A gladiator?
角斗士只在竞技场打斗
Gladiators only fight in the games.
难道你不想像凯撒一样
当一名出色的罗马战士？
Wouldn't you rather be a great
Roman warrior like Julius Caesar?
我是麦希穆斯，罗马的拯救者
I'm Maximus, the savior of Rome!
罗马的拯救者？
The savior of Rome?
谁说的？
And who said that?
卢赛斯在哪？
Where's Lucius?
他和皇帝在一起
He's with the Emperor, my lady.
- 她不可能那样做
- 不，是真的
- She couldn't.
- Yes, she did.
她从篮子里把它拿出来
She took it from a basket
把它放在她的胸口，就在她心脏的正上方
and pressed it to her breast,
right here above her heart.
- 它咬在她的胸口上？
- 是的
- It bit her in the breast?
- Yes.
你知道吗？卢赛斯，有时候那些皇室的小姐
You see, Lucius, sometimes royal ladies...
为了爱可以做出一些非常奇怪的事
behave very strangely and do very
odd things in the name of love.
- 我觉得很愚蠢
- 我也觉得
- I think it's silly.
- So do I.
So do I.
姐姐，过来加入我们
Sister, join us.
我在说故事给卢赛斯听
I've been reading to dear Lucius.
- 我也在念
- 没错
- I've been reading too.
- Yes.
他是个很聪明的小男孩
有一天他会成为了不起的皇帝
He's a very clever little boy.
He'll make a grand emperor one day.
我们在读伟大的安东尼和他在埃及的冒险
We've been reading about the great Mark
Antony and his adventures in Egypt.
还有埃及女王用蛇自杀的故事
The queen killed herself with a snake.
我还没告诉你发生在我们祖先身上的故事
And just wait until you hear
what happened to our ancestors.
如果你很乖，明天晚上
我会说克狄亚斯皇帝的故事
If you're very good, tomorrow night I'll
tell you the story of Emperor Claudius.
他遭到背叛…
He was betrayed...
被身边最亲的人…
by those closest to him.
他自己的亲人
By his own blood.
他们在黑暗中商议
They whispered in dark corners,
并且偷偷在半夜出去…
and went out late at night,
共同密谋
and conspired.
但是克狄亚斯皇帝知道他们有阴谋
But the Emperor Claudius knew
that they were up to something.
他知道他们像蜜蜂一样忙进忙出
He knew they were busy little bees.
有天晚上，他和其中的一个人谈话…
And one night he sat down with one of them,
他看着她…
and he looked at her,
他说…
and he said,
告诉我你们的计划…
"Tell me what you've been doing,
小蜜蜂…
busy little bee,
不然我会杀死你最亲的人
or I shall strike down those dearest to you."
“你会看到我身上沾满他们的血”
"You shall watch as I bathe in their blood."
而皇帝的心早就碎了
And the Emperor was heartbroken.
小蜜蜂伤他比任何人都深
The little bee had wounded him more deeply
than anyone else could ever have done.
卢赛斯，你认为接下来会发生什么？
And what do you think happened then, Lucius?
我不知道，舅舅
I don't know, Uncle.
小蜜蜂会告诉他所有的事
The little bee told him everything.
开门，我们是奉皇帝的命令！
Open, in the name of the Emperor!
帕西蒙！
Proximo!
奉皇帝的命令，把大门打开！
Open the gates in the name of the Emperor!
快开门！
Open the gates!
帕西蒙，快开门
Open the gates, Proximo!
老头，你想找死吗？
Do you want to die, old man?
拿去
Here.
东西都准备好了
Everything is prepared.
看来你赢得你的自由了
It seems you have won your freedom.
帕西蒙，当个好人是否会替你惹上麻烦？
Proximo, are you in danger
of becoming a good man?
- 裘巴
- 反抗皇帝的人都得死！
- Juba.
- All enemies of the Emperor die!
快开门！
Open the gates! The Emperor commands!
用力拉！
Pull!
快冲！派一队人马去左边！
Move! Two columns on the left!
我只需要机会脱身，千万别做无谓的牺牲
I only need moments, so do not
be careless with your lives.
不想被卷入这件事的，回到你的囚室去
If you don't want any part of
this, go back to your cells.
麦希穆斯，我们会留在这里帮你
We'll wait here for you, Maximus.
- 勇气和荣誉
- 走
- Strength and honor.
- Go!
勇气和荣誉
Strength and honor.
瞄准，拉弓！
Aim! Break the bars!
马卡斯奥里勒斯
帕西蒙
一切终归尘土
Shadows and dust.
麦希穆斯！
Maximus!
对不起
- I'm sorry.
- No!
事情都解决了
It's done.
我的外甥该如何处治？
And what of my nephew?
他母亲该如何处治？
And what of his mother?
他们应该面对和她爱人相同的命运吗？
Should they share her lover's fate?
我应该网开一面吗？
Or should I be merciful?
仁慈的康莫德斯
Commodus the Merciful.
从现在起，卢赛斯由我照顾
Lucius will stay with me now.
如果他的母亲…
And if his mother
用令我不快的眼神看我…
so much as looks at me
让我不悦的态度对我…
in a manner that displeases me,
他就会死
he will die.
如果她想抵死不从…
If she decides to be noble,
或者想自我了断…
and takes her own life,
他也会死
he will die.
至于你…
And as for you,
你会爱我…
you will love me,
如同我爱你一般
as I loved you.
你会帮我生育下一代…
You will provide me with
an heir of pure blood,
血统纯正的继承人…
so that Commodus
康莫德斯和他的后代子孙
将世世代代统治罗马
and his progeny will rule
for a thousand years.
我不够仁慈吗？
Am I not merciful?
我还不够仁慈吗？
麦希穆斯！
Maximus! Maximus! Maximus
我是个军人，我服从命令
I'm a soldier. I obey.
没有什么事是他不能承担的
Nothing happens to anyone that he
is not fitted by nature to bear.
麦希穆斯！
Maximus.
他们在为你欢呼
They call for you.
从将军沦为奴隶
The general who became a slave.
由奴隶成为角斗士
The slave who became a gladiator.
身为角斗士却敢对抗皇帝
The gladiator who defied an emperor.
一个震撼人心的故事
A striking story.
现在人们想要知道故事的结局
Now the people want to
know how the story ends.
只有死亡才能划下完美的句点
Only a famous death will do.
还有什么能比在竞技场上…
And what could be more glorious
亲自挑战罗马皇帝来得光荣呢？
than to challenge the Emperor
himself in the great arena?
- 你要跟我决斗？
- 有何不可？
- You would fight me?
- Why not?
你认为我会害怕？
Do you think I'm afraid?
我认为你一直都不敢面对我
I think you have been afraid all your life.
不像不败的麦希穆斯，有谁从来不害怕？
Unlike Maximus the Invincible,
who knows no fear?
一个我认识的人曾经说过
“死亡向所有的人微笑”
I knew a man who once said,
"Death smiles at us all."
“人们所能做的便是报以微笑”
"All a man can do is smile back."
我怀疑…
I wonder,
你的朋友在面对死亡时，也能够微笑吗？
did your friend smile at his own death?
你一定知道
You must know.
他是你的父亲
He was your father.
我知道你爱我的父亲…
You loved my father, I know.
可是我也爱他
But so did I.
对他的爱让我们变成兄弟，对不对？
That makes us brothers, doesn't it?
兄长，对我报以微笑吧
Smile for me now, Brother.
替他穿上盔甲，把伤口遮住
Strap on his armor. Conceal the wound.
成包围队形！
Ring formation!
Off with his head, Maximus!
昆塔斯，剑
Quintus, sword!
把你的剑给我
Give me your sword!
剑！给我一把剑！
Sword! Give me a sword!
收剑入鞘
Sheathe your swords!
麦希穆斯
昆塔斯
把我的人放了
Free my men.
恢复奎格斯议员的职位
Senator Gracchus is to be reinstated.
罗马的共和是个梦想
There was a dream that was Rome.
它应当被实现
It shall be realized.
那是马卡斯奥里勒斯的心愿
These are the wishes of Marcus Aurelius.
释放囚犯，快去
Free the prisoners! Go!
麦希穆斯
卢赛斯安全了
Lucius is safe.
去找他们吧！
Go to them.
你回家了
You're home.
罗马值得一个好人牺牲生命吗？
Is Rome worth one good man's life?
我们曾经相信
We believed it once.
让我们再次相信它
Make us believe it again.
他是罗马的战士
He was a soldier of Rome.
荣耀他
Honor him.
谁愿意来帮我？
Who will help me carry him?
现在我们都自由了
Now we are free.
我们会再见的
I will see you again.
只是时候未到
But not yet.
时候未到
Not yet.
献给我们的好友，奥利弗瑞德
[Mandarin Traditional R3]